<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Generall accomodations by addresse.</title>
            <author>Speed, Adolphus, fl. 1652-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4877A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E599_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206323</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865495</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865495</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117740</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93640)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117740)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 92:E599[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Generall accomodations by addresse.</title>
                  <author>Speed, Adolphus, fl. 1652-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Adolphus Speed.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 26. 1650:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Finance, Personal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117740:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>GENERALL ACCOMMODATIONS By Addreſſe.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoſoever ſhall have monies to let forth upon Intereſt, may have ſufficient ſecurity to his deſire, and ſuch preſent and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive directions for the more ſecure diſpoſing of his monies, ſo far tranſcending all manner of Adventure, that the reſult thereof, may (by many degrees) be more ſatisfactory and may more advantagiouſly extend and conduce to his content: ſee the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall be provided for a purchaſe of what proportion ſoever, either of lands in the Countrey or houſes here in the City, may have ſeverall particulars preſented to his conſideration, and full ſatisfaction to his deſire.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever hath occaſion to ſell lands, houſes upon Leaſe, &amp;c. or to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row monies upon lands, houſes, leaſes, rents, &amp;c. may be timouſly ſupplied to his deſire from 50 l. to 50000 l.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall deſire to encreaſe the talent, Divine Juſtice hath put into his hands, and will depoſite monies upon preſent Annuities or for eſtates in reverſion, that ſhall appear to the eye of judgement exceeding advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous, may have ſatisfactory compliancy to the full accompliſhment of his expectation; or whoſoever will give reaſonable ſatisfaction for monies during life, may have conſiderable ſums ſeaſonably parted with, upon honeſt and conſcionable terms.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever hath occaſion for a neceſſary houſe, or ſhall deſire to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided with convenient lodgings, furniſhed or otherwiſe, or ſhall be minded to be dieted, either wholly or at meals, as an Ordinary, of what condition or degree ſoever, they may have full information and ſatisfaction, with as much content as may be expected or deſired; Or whoſoever ſhall deſire to take a convenient Manſion neer <hi>London,</hi> or within twenty miles thereof, or part of an houſe or lodgings, with their diet or otherwiſe: they may have ſuch Information and Intelligence, as cannot but abundantly correſpond with their expectations; Or whoſoever ſhall have an inclination to take a convenient Houſe or Farme in the Countrey, by leaſe for yeares or lives,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117740:2"/> whereby they might continue to themſelves a convenient competency for their ſupport and livelihood; they may (in purſuance of their deſires) have plenary Intelligence from moſt part of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> and may further (according to their capacities) be directed and furthered to more fructiferous imployments under ſome eminent neighbouring Gentleman, that may (by vertue of their relation and recourſe) happily become their Landlord, &amp;c. or whoſoever ſhall be willing to part with ſuch habitation or place of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, of what proportion ſoever, or in what part of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland</hi> ſoever by hinting their pleaſures, all induſtry will not be wanting, at leaſt ſo much as may occaſion them inheritors of their deſires.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall be minded to buy any goods that <hi>London</hi> doth afford, either for apparell or otherwiſe, may be furniſhed at the firſt and beſt hand, at equitable rates, with all clarity and ſerenity, and with forbearance of their monies for the preſent or otherwiſe, or ſhall deſire to have their wants ſupplied with any kind of houſhold-ſtuffe, at the firſt or ſecond hand, as lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, pewter, braſſe, all ſorts of hangings, or other requiſites, appertaining to houſhold affairs, they may have their choice either by parcels as they have need, or the full furniture of an houſe from executors, or from ſuch as have occaſion to give up houſe-keeping, &amp;c. and conſtant information where, with whom, and upon what conditions they may be had. Or whoſoever ſhall have commodities to ſell, or what vendible commodities ſoever ſhall come from beyond the Seas, or out of the Country, either in great par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels or otherwiſe, upon information thereof at my Lodgings, they may have divers make addreſſe unto them, and may inſtantly vend whatſoever they ſhall have remaining by them.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall loſe any Papers, Books of Accompt, or any other conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable thing, whereas the finder may deſire reſtitution to the owner, by leaving notice thereof at my Lodgings, there may happen a reciprocall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation between them. Or whoſoever ſhall have goods ſtoln, as hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or any other cattell, may by deſcribing the marks, &amp;c. with other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary explanatory obſervations, have ſuch an expeditious courſe taken, by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of bils throughout the City, the Market Townes and Faires, within a conſiderable diſtance, and by all other Scrutinies for ſuſpicious perſons about the City, together with ſuch other probable and imaginable expedients, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually proſecuted and purſued, as may conſequently render reſponſible inferences of diſcovery, how to recover their goods again.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall deſire to be entertained as a Gentlemans Chaplain, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, Secretary, Steward, &amp;c. or ſhall be capable of preferment, eſpecially youth of what degree ſoever, may have ſuch directions and furtherance as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117740:2"/> may very much tend to their advancement; Or whoſoever ſhall need any ſuch ſervant, either for Clerks or Apprentices with ſufficient ſummes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, or any other ſervant of what quality or condition ſoever, or any that would be ſet a work in their faculties, &amp;c. they may be ſufficiently accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated to their deſires; Or if they need any that are expert and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in teaching Muſick, Short-writing, &amp;c. or any Artiſt whatſoever, or Maſters of bodily exerciſe, as Dancing, Fencing, &amp;c. they may have ſuch that will (according to the diſpenſations God hath conferred upon them) endevour to ingratiate themſelves to their eſteems, and ſome of the ſame qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications that will occaſionally evidence their willingnes by their induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous obſervancy to conform themſelves as domeſtick, that are men of known Truſt, Government and Integrity.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall have ſuits in Law to commence, or ſhall happen into any kinde of litigious controverſies, diſcordancies and competitions of what nature ſoever, or ſhall be priſoners, &amp;c. they may have their doubts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, matter of fact ſtated, ſubſtantially propoſed, and methodically diſgeſted with ſeaſonable directions upon eaſie tearms, without Retardings or Remoraes, and with the contribution of the concurrent opinions and free advice of the moſt candid and ingenious judgements that will ſtand by them in their juſt rights, and may happily addreſſe them unto ſome that ſhall (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out partiality) reſume the purſuit of the buſineſſe for them by right, or elſe make an amiable and an amicable compoſition and tranſaction of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for their beſt advantage with their Adverſary in their behalf. And may have ſome always in a readineſſe to ſerve as Amanences or Tranſcribers, and to draw and engroſſe all ſorts of Conveyances, Bils of Chancery, and ſuch like, with all manner of Bonds, Petitions, and whatſoever elſe may relate to ſuch that are Maſters of their Pen.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall have debtors that skulk and are latent in any part of <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. they may have ſuch reall and pertinent courſes obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and peracted for their diſcovery, and for recovery of their debts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may be made willing (if able) for all conſcionable performances, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall need an Agent or Solicitor, and ſhall deſire the common Intelligence of Publique State-affaires, and other communicable occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, may have all honeſt and faithfull ſervices performed, with what reſpective credentials and conſiderable obligements, ſhall bee neceſſarily required in reference and order to ſuch employments.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall be minded to undertake an office, or place of preſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, and ſhall deſire to be negotiated in any ſuch condition, may be ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117740:3"/> advertiſed very much tending to their future content and ſatisfaction. And ſuch that will part with an office or place of benefit for preſent profit, they may finde (by addreſſe) how to compaſſe their deſires; and thoſe that ſhall bee able to give. Intelligence of any ſuch office, &amp;c. which may happen by the ſickneſſe or death of any officer, or by miſdemeanours, being themſelves not capable to execute the ſame, upon their diſcovery they may be ſufficiently conſidered and rewarded therefore. Or if any man living remote ſhall be able to diſcover any materiall thing obvious to his obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which may be advantageous to the Publique, or to himſelf, not being able to repair to <hi>London,</hi> to advance his deſigne, upon intimation thereof by Letters or otherwiſe, he may have all prevalent advantages effectually purſued to promote the execution thereof, without putting himſelf to the charge of a great journey at adventure, and a condigne recompence procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the benefit which thence may accrew to the publique or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, with as much reality and ſincerity, as if hee himſelfe were preſent and able to proſecute the ſame.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall be ſo inſtrumentall to their own happineſſe and future content, to avoid the pernicious effects of ignorance in their children, and to endeavour the right framing of their ſtudies to the ready attainment of vertue and knowledge during their flexibility (according to the order of duty, and the talent committed to them, whereof they muſt be accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) may (in caſe of ſuch concernment) have ſuch excellent deſignes illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto them, that thoſe parents that are truly generous and carefull of their childrens good, cannot but exceedingly approve thereof, and very much incline thereunto: ſee <hi>pag.</hi> 11, 12.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall be inclinable to travell into any part beyond the Seas, may happily (by addreſſe) enjoy the bleſſings of ſuch unanimous conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, as may moſt neerly be conſiſtent with his diſpoſition, ſo that by a candid and a ſymphaticall participation and complacency in all occurrences, and by the entercourſe of mutuall friendſhip and correſpondency, there af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections may be ſo firmely tied together in the bonds of unity, and ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely woven within one another, that they may rationate, conſult and co-operate jointly in their travels, and the one may by their amicable coherency and combination meliorate improve and be helpfull unto the other in their abilities; and may further by men of worth, knowledge and experience, be reſpectively intelligenced, inſtructed and advertiſed of the manner and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of travelling into what part ſoever, how to ſteere his courſe with cautelouſneſſe and circumſpection, and to order and deport himſelfe in his Peregrinations for matter of expences and compliancy, and to diſcover and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117740:3"/> decline all falſe repreſentat himſelfe with ſuch ſort of people as he ſhall obviate and be converfant with, and may be furniſhed with Gold for Silver upon all occaſions, and be recru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſupplyed with all conveniences whereſoever he ſhall come.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall have relation to <hi>Virginia,</hi> the <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> New <hi>England,</hi> or any other Country inhabited with Engliſh, or ſhall have cauſe to ſend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any of thoſe places, or would inhabited, or tranſplant himſelfe in thoſe parts, they may have all intelligence and expedients with as much convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy as maybe; And ſuch here in <hi>England</hi> that ſhall have meanes fall unto them in any of theſe Countries, or any there ſhall have the like in any part of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; would have commodities tranſported from the one unto the other or any other reciprocall negotiation, or entercourſe of friendſhip of what importance ſoever, and ſo likewiſe into any other Country, as <hi>France, Spaine, Holland, &amp;c.</hi> by their addreſſe and application according to their particular ends and concernments, they may have all accommodation that may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be afforded, and matters of conſcientious concernments compleatly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedited, and what equitable offices Chriſtianity and humanity may afford, they may aſſuredly enjoy withall faithfulneſſe and ſerenity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Diſcoveries.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IMprimis,</hi> to diſcover a certaintie to raiſe 2000. li. per <hi>Ann. de Claro,</hi> with leſſe then 200. li. Stock unhazarded, and beyond contradiction, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt aſperſion of Uſury, Extortion, Oppreſſion, engroſſing, or any unconſcionable, monopolizing or diſhonourable way whatſoever. This deſign may be advanced to a farre greater proportion, and exceedingly to the good of the publike.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> a certainty with 500. li. ſtock unhazarded to raiſe <hi>de Claro</hi> 1000. <hi>per Ann.</hi> and upwards, without aſperſion, as above, and without the leaſt ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary, inconvenience or prejudice to any whatſoever, but to a generall good, eſpecially to the poore with the free allowance of all the Country.</p>
               <p>Together with a certainty with leſſe then 500. l. ſtock unhazarded, to raiſe <hi>de Claro</hi> 1000. lib. and upwards, and ſo with leſſe or greater ſummes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably by honeſt, faire, and generous courſes as above.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> to diſcover a credible way without charge more then ordinary expen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, whereby an induſtrious man but of a reaſonable capacity and fortune,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117740:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> may contrive to himſelfe 500. li. <hi>per An.</hi> and upwards, without prejudice to any, or diſhonour in the leaſt kind whatſoever unto himſelf.</p>
               <p>The like but with ſmall charges more then conveniency of livelyhood, whereby a man of an ingenious and a generous condition, may be compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, facill, and conſcionable waies, gaine 10000. li. <hi>per An.</hi> and upwards, with as much freedome, ſincerity and regularity as with the particulars above written.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> with leſſe then 50. li. ſtock conſtantly viſible and no way indangered to advance <hi>de Claro</hi> 10000. li. <hi>per An.</hi> ſeverall wayes, with all claritude and uprightneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> to make in all probability with 200. li. in three yeares 400. li. and in three yeares more to make the 400. li. 800. li. and in three yeares more to make the 800. 1600. li. without adventure by ſea, and ſo with leſſe or greater ſummes proportionably, by even honeſt and charitable wayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> to diſcover 500. li. <hi>per An.</hi> during life, which may eaſily be obtained, being no way diſadvantagious to the publike, or to any in particular.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> ſeverall other feiſible deſignes eaſie to be injoyed by thoſe that will uſe the meanes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> in all reality, to diſcover a way to advantage the publike many 1000. li. <hi>per an.</hi> eaſily to be put in practiſe, which will be generally allowable without prejudice to any whatſoever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> with 30. li. to raiſe within the compaſſe of 18. yeares 10000. li.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> a late experiment to make Tin here in London or in the Country at 20. for 5. benefit; and to make Steele braſſe, and Copper with very great profit: and to make Iron out of Pit-coale, and Sea-coale.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> to make Salt-peter to ſerve all the three Nations cheaper then any without digging of houſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> a deſigne with 200. li. charge and two mens labours to raiſe <hi>de Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> 5000. li. <hi>per. An.</hi> and upwards.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> wheras <hi>Middletons</hi> Mines (as it is reported) was never worth 16. li. <hi>per An.</hi> to diſcover Mines of 20. li. and 30. li. a Tunne, holding Silver out of Lead Oare, which by art may be advanced a 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. part by a new inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> there are Copper Mines within the three Nations, holding as much or rather more then the Queen of <hi>Sweathlands</hi> doth, and being managed it might ſave this Common-wealth 100000. li. <hi>per An.</hi> and ſet many poore at worke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> an undeniable manifeſtation, whereby every houſekeeper within <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland,</hi> may for a penny disburſed advantage themſelves 8. d.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117740:4"/> 
                  <hi>per</hi> week or thereabouts throughout the yeare, and ſo continually by a way eaſily communicable, and conſtantly comfortable, as well to the poore as the rich, and to the laſt at the leaſt a quadrible Emolument.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> a way(under God) whereby all food of fleſh may be conſtantly under the rate of 2. d. the pound throughout the Common-wealth without impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of of rates, reſtraint of the ordinary free uſe thereof, by a percimonious abſtinency, and without injunction of the too much neglected, and the moſt ingratefully diſregarded bleſſing of fiſh offered to our endeavour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> that Bread-corne (according to the ſtore God hath bleſſed this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with) may be cheaper, and farre more plentifull without reſtraint of quantity, impoſition of rates by courſe of juſtice, and without relation to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation, and the too too much ſuffered abuſe of exportation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> that Horſes may be kept fat and in hart, &amp; enabled to work and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell as formerly, without Hay, and a good part of the ordinary proportion of Oats uſually allotted unto them ſaved, and ſo in like manner Swine, and all ſorts of Poultry, may be fed fat and kept conſtantly in good liking, ſaving one part in three of the uſuall proportion of Oates ordinarily given unto them throughout the Common-wealth, and ſo eſpecially for Hunting-dogs; That Graine having been the chiefeſt and moſt comfortable preſervation of the poore from periſhing, being ſtill for the moſt part their conſtant food.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> divers undeniable wayes to returne conſtantly 20. for one with leſſe then an Acre of Ground, and ſo accordingly with many Acres, without the labour, toile, and charges, as uſually with Corne, and to make 30.40. &amp;, 50. li. an Acre <hi>per Annum</hi> in ſeverall parts of England, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> to make 10. li. an Acre <hi>per An.</hi> of the worſt Paſture Ground without plowing or ſowing, and ſo with many Acres in ſeverall parts of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> after ſeven yeares, and ſo conſtantly to make of the worſt ſort of meadow 10. li. an Acre <hi>per Annum,</hi> and ſo with many Acres in ſeverall parts of <hi>England</hi> without plowing, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> an Engine to contrive water from 20. yards depth, to drive a Mill conſtantly, ſo far as a Levell ſhall convey the water.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> to cleanſe any Country River of the mudde, though very deep with mudde and water, without diverting the courſe of the River, or uſe of Boats, or ſtanding in the water, by which meanes the River may be let down from overflowing, the banks much raiſed, and the grounds improved thereby. And ſo to empty Moats and Ponds of the mudde, without caſting or letting the water forth, or going into the water, or uſe of Boats: and ſo to emptie any Pond or Mote of the water if there be no paſſage by Sluces, os Ditches, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out caſting the ſame, or going into the water.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:117740:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> an Engine lately deviſed, whereby water may be contrived to dry Hillie and ſtirrill grounds, by which meanes they may be made more fertill, and afford far more profit then formerly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> a late rare diſcovery to prevent the ſmuttineſſe of Corne, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeverall large fields not farre from <hi>London,</hi> and in many other places where the Corne was conſtantly ſpoiled therewith, and after this experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there was hardly a Corne amiſſe, being very ſound, and farre more fruitfull, and the grounds exceedingly improved thereby.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> a diſcovery of conceiled Lands which King <hi>Iames</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> were couzoned of, worth thouſands <hi>per Annum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> a way to take red or fallow Deere with a baite, as eaſily as you do Fiſh, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> to put in a ſtock with a ſufficient Brewer, the monies ſecured, and to have halfe the benefit aſſured, with conſtant and very great profit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> a way lately deviſed, whereby an active man being accommodated with conveniences of livelyhood, may put himſelfe into credible imployment, and gaine thereby a 100. li. <hi>per Annum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> to diſcover a Mine of Coales, vety conſiderably convenient for ſale, not known to any but my ſelf, the Ingeneere whom I imployed therein being lately dead, whereby might be raiſed (all charges borne) at leaſt a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pound <hi>per annum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> Iron, Stone, Mills, Woods, and all other Requiſites whereby may be raiſed (beyond exceptions) at leaſt 1000. li. <hi>per annum de Claro,</hi> which may be made apparent beyond contradiction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> a Mine of Lead eaſie to become by, lying upon the ſide of an Hill, whereby may be raiſed 500. li. <hi>per annum de Claro,</hi> and without hazard.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> to make Houſes of Office being but halfe full, never to be fuller, and being emptied, never to be full.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> to diſcover a way whereby one Horſe may draw in a Cart as much as five Horſes, and ſo throughout <hi>England;</hi> This I have ſeen performed with an ordinary Horſe in the fowleſt wayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> an Inſtrument whereby the halfe part of all ſeed-corne may be ſaved throughout the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> a way whereby Brewing-veſſels may be contrived of wood, to ſerve in ſtead of Lead or Copper Veſſels, and halfe the Fewell (uſually ſpent) ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thereby.</p>
               <p>Together with a Manuſcript, whereby any man that can but read may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his infirmitie of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ickneſſe by the cauſes, ſymptomes and other apparan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and diſcourſes at large, &amp;c. with the obſervation of diet before and after,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117740:5"/> &amp;c. Then a manifeſtation of the remedies covenient and neceſſary for all diſeaſes whatſoever, if curable, &amp;c. with the courſes of practice, and the experiments of moſt of the famous Doctors of theſe later times; Together with the collection (by travelling) of all the rare and excellent receipts of Phyſick and Chyrurgery: amongſt which, foure eccellent and exceeding ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefull wayes for the perfect curing of the Kings evill, and neither of them with the ſeventh childe, &amp; divers others maintainable re-experimented expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments, of Phyſick and Chyrurgery for all infirmities whatſoever,—☞—part whereof coſt neere 1000. li. atteſted by ſpeculative and practicall confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of piouſly learned and judicious men, with divers other moſt curious and lucriferous rarities, which could not be attained unto, without extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary great care, paines, and expences. Together with ſeverall eaſie and moſt excellent wayes to make the Hands, and Face faire, and to take out wrincles, fleckles, marks, ſpots, ſunne-burnings, or any ſuch deformity of the face, and to make them very cleere, &amp;c. with the neweſt experiments of all neceſſary diſtillations that ſhall be fitting and uſefull, and perfect directions for the timely gathering of all ſorts of Hearbs, Roots, Fruits, &amp;c. therefore, or for any other purpoſe, with the true manner of uſing them, and the plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary diſcovery of all the effects of ſimples, &amp;c. all rare and new devices and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments of Cookery, not any thing omitted, relating to the illuſtration thereof, with all phyſicall obſervations, naturall effects, operations, and co-operations of meats, &amp;c. The excellency or true knowledge whereof, will render an unexpreſſible delight to the becomming reflections of the moſt eminent, and make them beautifull in the eyes of all that are bleſt with vertuous inclinations. <hi>Item</hi> all kind of Juſes, Gellies, Sirrups, Reſtoratives, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatievs, cordials, cawdles, &amp;c. all ſorts of gallimauferies, kickſhawes, biskets, Wafers, &amp;c. ſeverall excellent wayes, Comfits, Preſerves, Conſerves, Quid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinies, all manner of Candid, &amp; dried fruits, Marchpaines, &amp;c. and either of theſe ſeverall exceellent wayes &amp; new inventions and deviſes. Together with the neateſt, compleateſt, and moſt experimentall ways of the due ordering, rectifying, reſtoring, &amp; refining of all ſorts of Wines, and to make very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant wines of Grapes here in <hi>England. Item</hi> Raſpaſſfe wines, &amp;c. divers ſorts of Hypocraſſe, and excellent good with water, and ſeverall other rare and ſingular deviſes belonging unto wines. <hi>Item</hi> to make Mathegline, Perrie, Sider divers wayes, and ſeverall other excellent and moſt pleaſant drinks; &amp; how to order Ale, &amp; Beere ſeverall wayes with Hearbs &amp; Spices, &amp;c. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all ſort of rich ſanative perfumes, pomanders, with ſeverall print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and impreſſions thereon, ſweet-waters, ſweet waſhing-balls, ſweet-bags, ſweet-powders, &amp;c. all colours of ſealing-wax, perfumed and otherwiſe,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117740:6"/> all ſorts of Wax-candles, and all the varieties, and rare inventions and ſecrets that have been deviſed in theſe kinds or otherwiſe whatſoever, with the new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt excellent experiments thereof diſcovered, for the moſt part, and collected by Gentlemen of ſingular eminent and excellent parts, out of the rareſt Repoſitories, and from the abſtracts of the moſt experienced La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and Gentlewomen throughout the three Nations, and likewiſe from Gentlemen of great skill, judgement and practiſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe or any of them (although they cannot but reliſh well to thoſe that have pallets to taſt them) being for the moſt part of that ineſtimable value and dignitie, that by ordinary judgements they cannot be computed or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, and notwithſtanding the obſervations and atteſtations of men of honour and worth, and of the moſt juditious and candid of each reſpective profeſſion, yet in order to farther ſatisfaction, ſo far as they ſhall relate to health (the moſt deſirable of all earthly bleſſings) they may be confirmed and illuſtrated in a full and overflowing meaſure, by Gentlemen of known in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity and cleereneſſe, and by the moſt eminent and moſt deſerving Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners of theſe times, with their free advice, judgement, and direction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item</hi> ſeverall other great diſcoveries, exceeding beneficiall and of very great conſequence and importance which will be opportunely and cordially de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated with all candor, &amp;c. whereby whoſoever ſhall vouchſafe the peruſing of them, notwithſtanding the Compilors great loſſes and extreame ſufferings during theſe ſad diſtempers, the winde, ſtreame and Tide being alwayes againſt him) may apprehend him capable of doing good to any whatſoever, he having (for want of other imployments) devoted his whole life to theſe and other publike concernments, not daring to diſpaire of all fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable providence therein, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:117740:6"/>
               <head>For young Gentlemen.</head>
               <p>A Very choice place for conveniencie of Aire, Houſe-roome, Gardens, and walks moſt compleat, pleaſant and healthfull, ſeverall Maſters in the houſe, being abſolute, compleat Gentlemen and excellent Scholars; Theſe to teach them Hebrew, Greek, Latine, and French, by incomparably more methodicall, compendious and facill waies then formerly by any: by leſſening there former tedium by more then halfe. But above all they are to be taught the explanation of the Scriptures, and the principles of Religion by a devout, a moſt Religious and a piouſly learned Miniſter in the Houſe with them; And ſhall be taught to write by ſufficient Pen-men, and the beſt and moſt perfect way of ſhort writing, to take out Sermons, and to be able to convert them into Hebrew, Greek, Latine and French, as ſome of very tender yeares have lately done; They ſhall like wiſe be fully inſtructed in Heraldry by a deſerving Antiquary of very great knowledge therein; And ſhall have a skilfull and a well experienced Picture drawn to perfect them in that Art, if they ſhall delight therein: Maſters of Muſick, and Dancing-Maſters conſtantly to attend them, skilfull Fencers in a gentle and a moderate way to inſtruct and exerciſe them (for their Recreation) in that Science, Horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters with ſpeciall care and diligence to teach them all manner of Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, and ſeverall eaſie and well guided Horſes kept for them to thoſe purpoſes, with all neceſſarie Rings, and Riding-places provided for them: A Gentleman skilfull in all Military affaires to train them up (for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light) in the exerciſe of Armes.</p>
               <p>They ſhall further (if their Parents be ſo pleaſed) be taught the true ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentall naturall Phyloſophy and what is moſt neceſſary of the <hi>Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks,</hi> to wit, Arithmatick, Geometry, Geography, Coſmography, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective and Architecture, and alſo whatſoever is moſt excellent of the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> whatſoever belongeth to Fortification, beſieging, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending of places, fire-works, ordering of Battalies &amp; marches of Armes, &amp;c. A diſcreet care to be taken for ſuch wholeſome diet, as ſhall be moſt conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for them at all ſeaſons, with a direction of a Doctor of Phyſick very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and of exceeding great judgement, conſtantly in the Houſe to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look them, and to adviſe with their Parents and friends for the timely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of any infirmity they ſhall be inclinable unto, or ſhall happen unto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:117740:7"/>
               <head>For young Gentlewomen.</head>
               <p>A Very choice place for conveniency of aire, with a fair Houſe, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and ſpacious. Walks, very private, pleaſant and compleat, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Matron, with the help of other moſt diſcreet and skilfull ſervants to teach them all manner of Needle-works, Imbroidering, &amp;c. together with drawing on cloth for their works, the pourtraitures and fimilitudes of Birds, Beaſts, Fiſhes, Flowers &amp;c. and the full art and skill belonging there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; a learned and a moſt devour Miniſter in the houſe with them, to frame them rightly to the ready attainment of virtue and knowledge, by Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Explicating and expounding the Scriptures unto them, and to inſtruct them ſufficiently in prayer, and in the Principles of Religion, &amp;c. induſtrious and moſt judicious Pen-men, to teach them to write, cypher, and caſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts, eſpecially the beſt and moſt exact way of Short-writing, French women very vitreous, and well approved of, to teach them French, and conſtantly to bee converſant with them: ſeverall Maſters of Muſicke, ſinging and dancing Maſters, all choice men, grave, religious, and of excellent skill and governement. They ſhall likewiſe have given them to write out at convenient times, and be ſufficiently and moſt effectually inſtructed therein; all rare and excellent Receipts of Phyſick and Chyrurgery, ſo far as ſhall concerne their own healths, or be convenient for them, and all re-experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted experiments then unto belonging, not to be parallel'd for all infirmities whatſoever, &amp;c.—And ſo following according to the other particulars ſet down, <hi>pag.</hi> 9. at this mark—☞—unto the end of that clauſe.</p>
               <p>There ſhall likewiſe bee a diſcreet care taken for the proviſion of ſuch wholeſome diet as ſhall bee moſt convenient for them at all ſeaſons, with Doctors of Phyſick very famous and of great experience, repute and eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to have an influence upon them, and ſuch daily care of their healths that no conſiderable <hi>Punctilio</hi> in any circumſtance whatſoever, ſhall (under God) eſcape their obſervation.</p>
               <p>There ſhall likewiſe be a truſty and an able Solicitor in the houſe, who with the free advice of the moſt experienced Iudgements that are Councellors, together with the concurrence of the other Superintendents, <hi>viz.</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, Miniſter, Phyſitian, Steward, &amp;c. ſhall take care of all buſineſſes belonging to the Law, concerning the children that are or ſhall happen to be Orphants, and to aſſiſt and direct them as occaſion ſhall fall our, and to conſider with their neareſt and deareſt friends how to diſpoſe of their eſtates and means, by more fruitfull and ſecure ways then by Intereſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:117740:7"/>
               <head>For ancient Widows and Maids.</head>
               <p>VVHereas there are divers reall and ſingle-hearted Ladies and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, of virtuous and Chriſtianly diſpoſed mindes, captivated to the obedience of Chriſt, and hoping to have his Spirit to inhabite and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe them, whoſe affections are raiſed from the things of this earth, and are ſet on thoſe things that are above, they being bleſt with freedome, and with the happineſſe of their own diſpoſe, having unanimouſly declared their reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with conſtancy and ſerenity, ſo to continue firmly to the end, and to make themſelves (by the directing Spirit of Grace) amiable Lovers, ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Partners, and examplary Patterns of godly works, by abandoning and deſerting (as true Penitentiaries) the baſe earthlineſſe of their affections, the ſwelling pride of their hearts, the perverſe frowardneſſe of their wils, and avoiding all alurements that might withdraw them, and all oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that might provoke them from the duty of their vocation, by becom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming indeed and in truth impartiall lovers of righteouſneſſe, they not taking pleaſure in the ordinary way of living, as thoſe whoſe unbridled appetites are their whole Religion, or ſeeking themſelves, but the glory of the great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſer of all humane actions, in all their ways, ſtill re-minding the great account they have to paſſe at the laſt Audit, when the deareſt beloved, the chiefe Favourites, the fancy-feeding and flattering pleaſures of this world, ſhall ſhrink from us, and nothing but our own deeds and deſerts ſhall accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany us before the Iudgement Seat of God, making Chriſts Precepts the rule of their practice, and knowing that life is but a vapour, that appeareth but a little time and ſo vaniſheth away. Doe therefore during their ſojourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here fully determine, to keep themſelves in the knowledge and love of God, with an eager purſuit and delight thereof, looking for mercy of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt unto everlaſting glory and eternall life, and holding faſt their integrity, without wavering or falling from their ſteadfaſtneſſe, doe caſt themſelves upon the divine Providence, that is able to keep them from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and to preſerve them faultleſſe before the preſence of his glory with exceeding joy, being ſuch as the world (being ſhut up with gloomy dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) cannot comprehend, nor give unto them or take away from them, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king themſelves ready to ſaile towards the Haven of perfection, upon all opportunities of ſtronger Gailes, with full aſſurance, that when God is minded to bring his purpoſe to paſſe, he doth according to his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as ſeemeth good in the eyes of his heavenly wiſdome, put a rectified frame upon our wils, to perform thoſe things that are pleaſing in his ſight, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117740:8"/> ordaines means, whereby he doth offer himſelf unto us, and whereby wee are fitted to come unto him, in all holy converſation and godlineſſe. And for the preſent eſtabliſhing, perſeveration and advancement of theſe their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, truly vertuous and gracious determinations (whereunto all true hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtians are one way or another, if not engaged, yet concerned) there is a moſt compleat houſe and harbour of repoſe intended for them, and ſuch that are impartiall lovers of virtue, truth and righteouſneſſe, with all accommodation their hearts can wiſh or deſire, neere adjoining to the place where the young children (before mentioned) are to reſide; from whom (beſides the mutuall tranquillity, and almoſt unſpeakable harmonious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, they may moſt aſſuredly receive (under God) from each other) they may likewiſe enjoy all the content, and comfort that may poſſible be affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by their virtuous breeding, and all the regards, obſervancy and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance that may bee conceived or imagined conducible to ſuch a ſelect and bleſſed community, <hi>viz.</hi> a Miniſter, a Doctor of Phyſick, a Steward, &amp;c. men of worth, credit and eſteem, and of ſingular, eminent, gracious and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall parts, together with all other neceſſary officers, which for goodneſſe of life, religion, converſation, and all other abilities, are hardly to bee paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd, with all reſpective and conſiderable attendance of women ſervants al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed likewiſe by the houſe, that ſhall be beyond exceptions, beſides ſuch ſervants as they (if they pleaſe) may keep of their own, they allowing but a reaſonable proportion for their diets; And it is further ſo contrived, that all requiſites and needfull concernments ſhall bee provided for them at the beſt hand, and at the cheapeſt rates, both of Merchants and others; here in the City, and from all parts of <hi>England.</hi> And whatſoever is deſired extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, exceeding their conſtant competency of diet, ſhall bee ordered at all times in the diſcreeteſt manner, and ſhall be always in a readineſſe provided for them at their chambers, or otherwiſe, by the cooks, and other officers at command, with all diligence and reſpect, and with all content that may poſſible be expected, without the leaſt exaction of fees, &amp;c. but the full al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of every particular, at the rates they were provided, whereunto there ſhall be always a diligent care and circumſpection evidenced by the Steward and ſuch as are ſubordinate unto him, no ſervant being to be admitted into the houſe without letters of credency and ſufficient obligements for their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, and to be diſmiſt upon the leaſt miſ-behaviour whatſoever. There ſhall likewiſe be a learned and an eminent Councellour and Solicitour always at hand, able men of unqueſtionable truſt and uprightneſſe, conſtantly to take ſpeciall care of their eſtates, and with the furtherance, aſſiſtance, and concurrence of the ſuperiour officers, to ſecure the Gentlewomen from all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117740:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> worldly troubles, and to endeavour to diſpoſe of what ſhall belong unto them with ſuch ſecurity and advantage, that may aſſuredly acquit them from all diſturbance and unquietneſſe whatſoever. Which happy conjuncture, ſweet concordancy and conformity, may (with the bleſſing of the moſt High) who worketh all things after the counſell of his owne will, make them beautifull in the eyes of the faithfull; and by their gracious motives and incitations of encouragement, to render a great improvement and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement for the Plantation of piety, and to a further propagation of Chriſts Kingdome, and will be no ſmall comfort (in theſe evill times) unto faithfull ſouls, whoſe hearts arc filled with the joyes of the Spirit, and are kept by the power of God, through faith unto ſalvation, they looking for the bleſſed hope of the glorious appearing of the great God and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Ieſus Chriſt, who gave himſelfe for us, that hee might redeem us from all iniquity, and purifie unto himſelfe a peculiar people zealous of good works, who receiving the end of their faith, even the ſalvation of their ſouls, ſhall always rejoyce with joy unſpeakable and full of glory.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
